Ralph Crowley MD Papers Finding Aid
Oskar Diethelm Library
Ralph Crowley MD Papers
1927 - 1982
This collection contains the papers of Ralph Crowley, who was a New York psychoanalyst and former president of the American Academy of Psychoanalysis. The collection has 3 series: Harry Stack Sullivan, Non-Sullivan Papers, and Audiotapes.
2.09 linear feet (5 boxes)
Crowley, Ralph M.
Oskar Diethelm Library DeWitt Wallace Institute of Psychiatry: History, Policy and the Arts Weill Cornell Medical College 525 East 68th Street, Box 140 New York, NY 10065
1984.0001
Dr. Crowley bequeathed his papers, which arrived after 1984 through the efforts of his sons.
There are no access restrictions on this material.
Ralph Manning Crowley was born in Madison, Wisconsin in 1905 and received his M.A. in psychology in 1928 from the University of Wisconsin, where he was strongly influenced by Norman Cameron. Crowley became an analysan of Lionel Blitzsten, who introduced the psychodynamic approach to Crowley, and he began analytic training at the Chicago Analytic Institute. In 1934, he started residency training at the Sheppard and Enoch Pratt Hospital in Baltimore and completed his training at the Washington-Baltimore Psychoanalytic Society training program, where he first was influenced by Harry Stack Sullivan.
Crowley became a member of the faculty of the Washington-Baltimore Psychoanalytic Institute in 1938 and a Training Analyst in 1941. He moved to New York City in 1946 in order to set up a private practice. He was soon asked to be a faculty member and training and supervisory analyst at the William Alanson White Institute and, in 1948, he was made a Fellow. He helped organize the Low Cost Psychoanalytic Service of the Institute and was its Director and Director of Clinical Services from 1948 until 1960. He held distinguished consultantships and hospital appointments and was a Past President of the American Academy of Psychoanalysis and of the William Alanson White Psychoanalytic Society. He had approximately 65 publications to his credit at the time of his death in 1984.
Crowley, Ralph M.; Schizophrenia; Sullivan, Harry Stack, 1892-1949; Washington-Baltimore Psychoanalytic Society; William Alanson White Institute; Thompson, Clara, 1893-1958; Psychoanalysis; American Academy of Psychoanalysis
This collection contains the papers of Ralph Crowley, who was a New York psychoanalyst and former president of the American Academy of Psychoanalysis. There are 3 series in this collection.
Harry Stack Sullivan: This series primarily has Crowley’s notes pertaining to Sullivan’s psychoanalytic theories, including notes he took as a student of Sullivan while attending the Washington-Baltimore Psychoanalytic Society in 1935. Crowley prepared additional notes about Sullivan for a course Crowley taught at the William Alanson White Institute in New York City. This series also includes Crowley’s notes, drafts, and correspondence for a biography of Sullivan he was preparing. Of particular interest are several letters written in the 1970’s by Sullivan’s adopted son, Jimmie, concerning his initial relationship with Sullivan. Additional correspondence regards Crowley’s bibliography of Sullivan’s works. Also included in this series are published and unpublished articles written about Sullivan by individuals other than Crowley, as well as copies of some of Sullivan’s papers. There are also a small number of Sullivan’s personal papers such as photographs, a caricature, and copies of his medical school diploma and death certificate. Crowley identified contents of groupings of his papers by writing notes on brown manila envelopes. Some of these have been saved and are placed in the appropriate folders.
Non-Sullivan Papers: These records consist of general correspondence and reprints by Clara Thompson.
Audiotapes: This includes audiotapes about Sullivan, and several record a symposium held at Chestnut Lodge Research Institute in Maryland regarding various aspects of Sullivan’s psychoanalytic theories. There are both reel to reel and cassette tapes of the symposium. Included are presentations by Dorothy Blitsten, Patrick Mullahy, Marion Langer, and Clifton Read. One tape made by Crowley records versions of his biography of Sullivan. Crowley’s notes on the tapes, as well as correspondence, form part of this series. The quality of the tapes is frequently poor; portions of them are inaudible.
- Harry Stack Sullivan
  - Sullivan’s personal papers, including photographs, caricature by Henry Major, letter, copies of medical school diploma, and death certificate, c. 1945 - 1949 (Box 1)
  - Notes written by Crowley on books, articles, and a course taught by Sullivan in 1935 and 1944, 1935 - 1944 (Box 1)
  - Notes written by Crowley on books, articles, and a course taught by Sullivan in 1935 and notes for a course Crowley taught about Sullivan, c. 1935 - c. 1969 (Box 1)
  - “Sullivan as Clinician” Crowley’s supervision with Sullivan and notes on Sullivan, 1937 - 1938 (Box 1)
  - Retyped notes Crowley prepared on Sullivan, 1971 (Box 1)
  - Crowley’s notes on Sullivan’s views on schizophrenia, 1940 (Box 1)
  - Crowley’s notes on Sullivan’s life and correspondence and reprints about Sullivan, 1950 - 1973 (Box 1)
  - Notes and administrative letters on a course Crowley gave at the White Institute, 1969 - 1972 (Box 1)
  - Crowley’s notes re: Sullivan on therapy, 1969 - 1971 (Box 1)
  - Verbatim cases, Undated (Box 1)
  - Notes on Dr. Bullard’s reminiscences of Sullivan and Bullard’s obituary, 1972 (Box 1)
  - Crowley’s notes on Sullivan’s seminars and quotes, Undated (Box 1)
  - Crowley’s notes on Sullivan’s “Theory of Sexual Development” and essay “On the Difficulties of Teaching Sullivanian Interpersonal Theory, Undated (Box 1)
  - Crowley’s drafts of paper “Sullivan: Treatment of Psychosis”, Undated (Box 1)
  - Crowley’s quotes of Sullivan’s published writings, Undated (Box 1)
  - Crowley’s notes on Sullivan, Undated (Box 1)
  - Material re: Crowley’s biography of Sullivan including letter from Jimmie Sullivan, c. 1973 (Box 2)
  - Material re: Crowley’s biography of Sullivan for an encyclopedia article including letters from Jimmie Sullivan, c. 1973 (Box 2)
  - Crowley’s notes and outlines for his biography of Sullivan, c. 1973 (Box 2)
  - Letters sent to Crowley for his biography of Sullivan including letters by Helen Perry, 1962 - 1976 (Box 2)
  - Crowley’s draft of biography of Sullivan and other material re: Sullivan, 1970 - 1973 (Box 2)
  - Agenda for 1974 symposium on Sullivan and galley proof of Crowley’s short biography of Sullivan used in symposium, 1970 - 1974 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence and notes for Crowley’s biography of Sullivan, 1971 - 1976 (Box 2)
  - Notes and drafts of Crowley’s papers “Notes on Sullivan’s Approach to the Science of Man” and Sullivan’s “Concepts of Unique Personality”, 1970 - 1971 (Box 2)
  - Crowley’s correspondence re: bibliography and old bibliography, 1970 - 1976 (Box 2)
  - Crowley’s bibliography of Sullivan, 1970 - 1974 (Box 2)
  - Manuscript by Arthur David Robbins, “Harry Stack Sullivan: The Man or His Work”, 1980 (Box 2)
  - “Sullivan’s Approach in Therapy with his Comments on Particular Patients” by Jane Pearce, 1950 (Box 2)
  - Crowley’s essay re Sullivan’s importance, 1980 (Box 2)
  - Reprints of Sullivan’s papers, 1927 - 1948 (Box 3)
  - Articles about Sullivan, 1949 - 1962 (Box 3)
  - Articles about Sullivan, 1971 - 1982 (Box 3)
  - Glossary re: interpersonal dictionary and article by Herbert A. Rosenfeld “Infantile Anxiety and Psychosis”, 1962 (Box 3)
  - Articles written by David Elkind, 1972 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence and papers re: Sullivan including letters from Dorothy Blitsten, 1966 - 1977 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence with Lawrence Kubie, Norman Cameron, and others re: Harry Stack Sullivan and other matters, 1970 - 1975 (Box 5)
  - Comments made by Dexter Bullard re: Sullivan, 1969 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence and death certificate of Sullivan and correspondence re: other matters, 1949 - 1978 (Box 5)
- Non-Sullivan Papers
  - General correspondence, 1934 - 1975 (Box 3)
  - Reprints by Clara Thompson, 1942 - 1959 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence with Clara Thompson, 1945 - 1958 (Box 5)
- Audiotapes
  - Tape I of Sullivan symposium at Chestnut Lodge Research Institute re: homosexuality, catatonia, paranoia, etc., 1945 (Box 4)
  - Tape II of Sullivan symposium at Chestnut Lodge Research Institute on sexual behavior and classification, needs for intimacy and tenderness, lust, dynamism and loneliness, and schizophrenia, 1969 (Box 4)
  - Tape III of Sullivan symposium at Chestnut Lodge Research Institute on blushing, modes of experience, etc., 1945 (Box 4)
  - Tape IV of Sullivan symposium at Chestnut Lodge Research Institute on personal inventory and therapy, dream experience, conduct of therapy, etc. including Crowley’s notes on tape, 1945 (Box 4)
  - Two cassette tapes from published works of Sullivan “The Illusion of Personal Individuality”, Undated (Box 4)
  - Audiotape and Crowley’s notes from Sullivan tape on blushing, Undated (Box 4)
  - Copy of a Sullivan tape, unidentified, Undated (Box 4)
  - Tape of Dorothy Blitsten’s discussion of Sullivan and Crowley’s notes on tape recording, 1969 (Box 5)
  - Ralph Crowley on Sullivan as clinician and Patrick Mullahy on Sullivan in relation to Mullahy’s recent book and personal reminiscences and development of ideas, 1969 (Box 5)
  - Tape of Marion Langer and Clifton Read on Sullivan, 1971 (Box 5)
  - Tape of Crowley’s biographies of Sullivan, long and short versions, and outline of biography, 1974 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence re: Sullivan tapes, 1973 - 1975 (Box 5)